<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="areeb.site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="areeb.site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-02T13:02:48+00:00</updated><id>areeb.site/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Areeb SM’s website</title><subtitle>A personal webpage, built with [*al-folio](https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio) simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">I Read a Book! The Rise and Fall of a Brown Water Navy</title><link href="areeb.site/blog/2024/brownWaterNavy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Read a Book! The Rise and Fall of a Brown Water Navy"/><published>2024-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>areeb.site/blog/2024/brownWaterNavy</id><content type="html" xml:base="areeb.site/blog/2024/brownWaterNavy/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently happened to read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/62990195-the-rise-and-fall-of-a-brown-water-navy"><em>The Rise and Fall of a Brown Water Navy: Sarkhel Kanhoji Angre and Maratha Seapower on the Arabian Sea in the 17th and 18th Centuries</em></a>, written by Anirudh Deshpande and Muphid Mujawar. Admittedly I was particularly drawn to the idea of reading about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown-water_navy">brown water navy</a>, but the book focuses more on the Angres and <em>their</em> navy<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p> <p>That said, it’s still an illuminating case study on the interactions between a regional Indian authority and competing powers (Indian and colonial). One phenomenon familiar to the 21st-century reader is that of a regional force holding its own against a technologically superior foe using “home turf” advantages. In this case this takes the form of colonial powers fielding bigger and more heavily armed ships, and thus outgunning Indian ones. Indian powers tended to rely on a combination of land forces and <em>brown water</em> navies, as opposed to <em>blue water</em> ones (on the high seas)<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Knowledge of the coasts and their topography could be used to set ambushes and leverage experience with land combat into naval successes.</p> <p>Another is the nature of the competition between local Indian powers. Indeed, the Angres were often challenged by a coalition of a colonial power and an Indian one, the former attacking by sea and the latter overland. On the flip side, the Angres would themselves exercise autonomy (even issuing their own trade licenses), despite nominally owing fealty to the Maratha head.</p> <p>Power struggles around Maratha ascension in the Mughal wake are an integral part of the Angre story, with Kanhoji himself drawing legitimacy through the <em>saranjam</em> system that Rajaram was compelled to resort to.</p> <p>All in all, a solid read. It isn’t very long, making it quick work particularly if one is familiar with the players around the Konkan at the time. Would recommend.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>While navies fielded by other powers do enter the picture, their mention is restricted to their interactions with that of the Angre’s. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Tipu Sultan would try, but he wouldn’t get it done before his defeat. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="history"/><category term="non-academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sarkhel Kanhoji Angre and Maratha Sea Power on the Arabian Sea in the 17th and 18th Centuries]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Preprint!</title><link href="areeb.site/blog/2024/hmm-preprint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Preprint!"/><published>2024-01-26T06:26:39+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-26T06:26:39+00:00</updated><id>areeb.site/blog/2024/hmm-preprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="areeb.site/blog/2024/hmm-preprint/"><![CDATA[<p>We<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> have finally finished up a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14669">preprint</a> <a class="citation" href="#fritz2024hidden">(Fritz et al., 2024)</a> for our work on hidden Markov models<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> in the context of Markov categories <em>(woohoo!)</em>.</p> <p>We’ve been at it for a while, I’d in fact presented this work at the <a href="https://act2023.github.io/">Applied Category Theory 2023</a> conference<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> back in the August of 2023. Of course, we’ve added a fair bit since then. For instance, the material on smoothing was all written after the conference. Still, it’s good to finally have something out :D</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Tobias Fritz, Andreas Klingler, Drew McNeely, Yuwen Wang and I. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Sometimes called <em>state space models</em>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>The recording is on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PwI3oOXWWe8">YouTube</a>. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="preprints"/><category term="math"/><category term="bibliography"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Work on hidden Markov models in Markov categories]]></summary></entry></feed>